[Episode 31]
Black Bird eternal!
Blood Moon forever!
Welcome back, Your Highness!
You may all rise.
I have waited over ten years.
Finally, Your Highness has returned.
You are
the old clan chief?
Is it truly you, Your Highness?
You have truly returned.
Of the twelve clan elders, now only I remain.
Your Highness still remembers me.
Now I can die in peace.
Please drop your blood on the clan register
and offer it to the altar.
Then swear before the Black Bird
[Clan Register]
you'd restore our kingdom
to comfort the souls of the tragic dead.
Your Highness returns!
May we restore our land!
Ancestors above,
I, Murong Yao, though unworthy of this line,
command as the princess:
the state of Zhongwan
shall never be re-established.
Your Highness!
Your Highness, you've shattered
the hope of Zhongwan's people.
To not restore our kingdom
is to betray our ancestors.
Living is more important
than memorial tablets.
I only want to save the people of Zhongwan.
Black Bird eternal!
Blood Moon forever!
When I stain the altar with my blood,
the Black Bird will awaken completely.
Black Bird eternal!
Blood Moon forever!
We beg the Black Bird to open its eyes
and grant Her Highness
the will to restore our kingdom.
Your Highness,
the old clan chief's two sons
both died in battle over ten years ago.
His grandson died
on a snowy night while fleeing.
And he cried himself blind.
All these years, his only reason to live
was to see Your Highness one last time.
Because he firmly believed
that Your Highness would return.
For the other two
who volunteered to sacrifice themselves,
one had a son who died
building canals for the Ning Empire,
and the other had his entire family
buried alive when our kingdom fell.
My entire Shangguan family
all died at the hands of the Ning people.
Without the faith of restoration
to sustain us,
among all of us here,
not one could survive until now.
Your Highness, please get changed.
The princess of Zhongwan should not wear
the robes of an enemy queen.
Zhongwan attire suits Your Highness better.
Come, pay respects to our ancestors.
Ancestors above,
I, unworthy descendant Murong Yao,
have come too late.
To grant the people of Zhongwan
peace and prosperity
is my duty as the princess.
I'll never let war fall on Zhongwan again.
Your Highness, swear to the ancestors quickly
that you will restore our kingdom
and reclaim the realm.
Yin Qing, doesn't letting the people
live in peace
matter more than killing for restoration?
I have brought you back safely.
It's time for me to walk the path I must.
What is Your Highness going to do?
Ning has abolished
the perpetual servitude law.
The new policies will go through.
I shall return to Ning
as the princess of Zhongwan
and negotiate peace with the Emperor of Ning
to seek a way forward for Zhongwan's people.
Do you know what the Wannu Camp
is going through?
Do you think that a few new policies
from Ying Gua
can erase the suffering and humiliation
of the Zhongwan people?
How has the Ning Empire
treated us all these years?
When the day of restoration comes,
they must pay all the debts.
Restoring the kingdom
is your obsession, not mine.
I only want to save my people.
Sir, perhaps we can resolve this
without bloodshed
in exchange for Zhongwan's peace--
Get out.
You are the princess of Zhongwan.
What will it take for you
to come to your senses?
You'll restore our kingdom.
Come, say it to the ancestors.
You'll restore our kingdom!
Yao.
You're bleeding.
I'll join you.
Yin Qing, are you crazy?
I'm not crazy.
I am Shangguan Zhao, your Shangguan.
My Shangguan died over ten years ago.
The one alive is the Yin Qing
who gave me the Rain Bell
and told me
that even the fiercest storm will pass.
There is no Yin Qing in this world at all.
To restore our kingdom,
I can even grovel and flatter Ying Gua.
No one can stop my cause
of restoring our kingdom,
including you.
Your path
leads to nothing but a grave for everyone.
No matter how hard the path I seek,
it's still a path for the living.
Guards.
Yao,
after we kill Ying Gua
and destroy the Ning imperial family,
we will go play hide-and-seek,
just like when we were children.
I'll leave the restaurant to you.
Keep the books as usual.
If anyone important asks,
say I'm out of town to visit family.
Ms. Yan, it's too dangerous
for you to go alone.
Mr. Shen, you've come at the right time.
Quick, persuade Ms. Yan.
Zhao Cai.
You're going to find her?
That day, I drew my sword
for the Ning Empire.
If she desires no restoration,
I will never harm her in the slightest.
What if she desires that?
If I protect her and oppose you,
will you kill me as well?
There won't be such a day.
If you dare harm her in the slightest,
I will never forgive you.
I don't care whether
she is from Ning or Zhongwan.
I only care about her.
I'm going to find her right now.
Fu Zhi,
His Majesty will lead the campaign himself.
I'll take you to her.
Miss, you dropped your ink stick.
Thank you, Miss.
I planted this pot
of Fragrant Abundance myself.
It's a gift for you.
You can place it on your desk,
and it's best for calming the mind.
Indeed, it smells good.
On our first day,
let's turn this cheerless Censorate
into the best local office, shall we?
Alright.
You grew up in hardship,
yet you still achieved the Triple First.
I am truly filled with admiration.
I don't know how to express my feelings.
I only hope these items
can warm the coldness of your past.
Zhi Li, there's no need to cry.
It's all in the past.
Everything ahead is new.
If you believe he's a good man,
why not give each other a chance?
He is so good.
I always feel that I don't deserve him.
Meng, tell me,
why did I agree to this marriage
in the first place?
When a person is in extreme pain,
they always need to find support.
And Nian is the lamp
that guides you forward in the fog.
Because you know each other,
and he can give you
the peace of mind you need.
But I do care about him.
I can't stand to see him hurt.
I can bear to see him sad
because of me even less.
You don't need to feel guilty.
I just hope you can slowly
let down your guard.
Nian is worth it.
This is the farewell wine.
You want to stop me?
I trust her.
Even as a remnant of Zhongwan,
she will not harm the Ning Empire.
Nian, I want to go on the campaign with you
to find Meng.
Zhi Li, no matter how deep
your personal friendship is,
you can't let personal feelings
interfere with state affairs.
The front line is dangerous.
Miss Yan and Zhi Shu will be in charge
of the grain escort.
They can avoid the battlefield danger,
but I must be at the front line personally.
If you accompany me,
whenever the beacon fires are lit,
I will first think of your safety
and get distracted.
But I'm really worried about Meng,
and you too.
Zhi Li,
now,
do you like me even a little?
You said
this peach wood brings good luck
and protects the wearer.
Wear it.
I want you to come back safely.
I understand.
I will set out at the hour of Yin tomorrow.
I won't disturb you tonight.
Nian.
Zhi Li.
My lady,
before the Marquis left,
he instructed us to take good care of you.
This morning, we heard you cough a little.
And with the weather
getting colder these days,
we've prepared some cold medicine.
It dispels the cold and boosts you.
[Nine Nine Nine Cold Medicine]
Your Highness still wants to escape?
I'm going to find a way
for Zhongwan's people.
Mr. Shangguan has ordered
that if Your Highness escapes,
all the guards and maids
watching over Your Highness
will be sent to the Wannu Camp.
There, bodies pile up
at the alley entrances every day.
Some were strangled at the city gate
for no more than taking half a moldy pancake.
I hope Your Highness will let them live.
If you truly regard me as the princess,
why does every word I say
not match a single threat from him?
These past few days back in Zhongwan,
I always dream of Yin Qing.
In the three years
he was by my side in the Censorate,
always smiling and joking,
making witty remarks
and finding ways to make me laugh.
Every day, he cooked a table full of dishes,
saying it was to reward me and Zhi Li.
Whenever there was danger,
he would always shield us without hesitation.
How could someone like that
have become like this now?
Your Highness,
Mr. Shangguan
is a man of kindness at his core.
You have feelings for him?
When Zhongwan fell,
I was sent to Qingzhou as a slave,
taken in by that beast of a magistrate
as a household prostitute,
tormented day and night.
Those days were even more agonizing
than in the Wannu Camp.
It was Mr. Shangguan who saved me
when I was most desperate
and gave me a new identity,
allowing me to live with dignity.
No matter what he does,
I will stay by his side
and support him.
So you should help me even more
to keep him from going down the wrong road.
I want to go to the Wannu Camp.
Take me there.
- Hurry up!
- Stop drinking!
- Go quickly!
- Get to work!
- Get up!
- No slacking off!
Hurry!
- Get up!
- Be quick about it!
I'm talking to you!
Get up! Are you getting up?
Your Highness,
the Wannu Camp is heavily guarded.
We can only watch from afar.
In the Wannu Camp,
mining, building tombs, digging canals,
wherever there is deadly labor,
our Zhongwan people are driven to it.
It has been over ten years.
Mr. Shangguan tried bribing officials
and organizing escapes.
But once branded with the slave mark,
even to the ends of the earth,
one will be dragged back and executed.
Your Highness,
you are the only one
who can give these people hope to live.
Your Highness, for every day you delay,
Zhongwan gains dozens more corpses.
You've seen the Wannu Camp,
and you still won't restore our kingdom?
If you can find a way
to avoid shedding any Zhongwan blood,
I will resolve to restore our kingdom.
As long as you and I are married,
we can draw Beijian into the fray
to charge into battle for us.
I agree.
But I have three conditions.
First, all of Zhongwan shall obey my orders,
including you.
Second, the alliance with Beijian
must be under my lead.
Third, from now on,
you shall no longer threaten me
with any person or any matter.
I agree to all of them.
Your Highness,
you have finally awakened.
I watched my father and mother die
before my eyes
and saw the people of Zhongwan
branded with the slave mark of Ning.
I am the last bloodline
of the Zhongwan royals.
I'll take back our realm with my own hands.
The Black Bird returns.
I swear to follow Your Highness to the death.
Since you acknowledge me as the princess,
you should speak to me on your knees.
I will not only be the princess.
Since I'm the last of the Zhongwan royals,
I will become
the first ever empress of Zhongwan.
On the day of my coronation,
it will be the time of our wedding.
As you command.
Yeqi has sent a treaty of alliance,
and Taishui has sent their surrender.
Di Nian, Zhi Shu,
these two battles were fought
with the same mettle as the late marquis.
- I'm honored to have not failed.
- General Di!
Your Majesty,
Beijian has blocked our grain route
for over seven days.
The wounded are short on medicine,
and it's critical.
Fu Zhi has contacted the prefectural guilds.
They've agreed to pool resources.
Your Majesty, I pledge everything I have.
I will personally see to it that the supplies
reach our army in time.
If this war is lost,
as the head of the trade routes,
you'll be the first to be purged.
And all that you have painstakingly built
over the years will be lost.
If the country is lost, what use is a home?
I only hope this war can end soon
and I can meet Meng soon.
The first herbs will be at the camp
in three days.
You see the larger cause, Miss Yan.
On behalf of our soldiers, I thank you.
Zhi Shu, escort Miss Yan
through the western canyon
to gather supplies and protect her safety.
I will ensure she is unharmed.
Your Majesty, urgent report!
The Zhongwan rebels
have sent a message by arrow,
claiming that Miss Meng...
Say it.
[Urgent Report]
Miss Meng intends to declare herself empress
and establish her own rule.
Beijian cuts off our army's grain.
Zhongwan shakes our morale.
They want to put Your Majesty in a bind
both inside and out.
Your Majesty, we must strike first
to uproot the threats entirely.
Shen Zhi Shu.
For generations, my family has vowed
to protect His Majesty
and preserve the Ning Empire.
Even if you hate me,
I must stand firm in my position today.
As the princess, Meng Ting Hui
is the hope for all Zhongwan people
to live on.
Whether she becomes the empress or not,
in the current situation,
this may be her only choice.
Even if Beijian and Zhongwan
form an alliance,
we still have a countermeasure.
Your brother's death in the Ning Empire
[Beijian's First Prince]
was the doing of the Ning Emperor Ying Gua.
Now that Yeqi has submitted
and Taishui can hardly withstand it,
only by joining forces
can we resist the Ning Empire's
hundred thousand cavalry.
Zhongwan has been destroyed for many years,
and you are nothing but a stray dog.
What do you have to bargain with us?
Because the princess of Zhongwan
is Ying Gua's beloved.
Moreover, she and I have long been betrothed
and will be married soon.
Shangguan Zhao, here in my tent,
with your empty words,
you expect to win the trust
of my Beijian cavalry?
You are merely the leader
of the Blood Moon Society.
Beijian allies only with a true ruler.
In that case, would you be willing
to ally with me, First Prince?
Zhongwan has been destroyed for many years.
What do you have
to propose an alliance with me?
For the battle between Beijian and Ning,
let me teach you how to win.
He will deploy heavy troops here,
[Jinxia Pass]
so we should take Xigu Pass.
Kill!
Beijian will detour through Xigu Pass.
Di Nian, lead your troops
to intercept the enemy's pursuit.
Xigu Pass is weakly defended.
Why would Your Majesty--
Precisely because it is weakly defended,
it will be her choice.
She knows I will set an ambush
on the trade route,
and I know she'll take an unexpected way.
How do you, the princess of Zhongwan,
know the deployment of the Ning army?
Because he has calculated
that I will calculate every move of his.
If you want to win,
you must make him think
everything is under his control.
In this world, no one knows her thoughts
better than I.
Tonight, I will lead elite troops
to personally scout the enemy camp.
- Di Nian.
- I will lead troops to make a feint.
Fu Zhi, you haven't eaten or drunk all day
while gathering supplies.
Eat something.
I'm not hungry.
Must we be like this?
Since you raised your sword against Meng
in the Sacred Ancestral Hall,
is there still 'we'?
Shen Zhi Shu,
you know full well
how important Meng is to me.
My mother died early.
Growing up,
only Meng stayed with me and cherished me.
If it weren't for her being with me,
I would have gone with my mother long ago.
Yet you actually had the heart to kill her.
Fu Zhi,
I am not just your Shen Zhi Shu.
And my sword was not pointed
at your Meng that day
but at the princess of Zhongwan,
a traitor who intended to destroy the court
and the Ning Empire.
Meng has done so much good
for the Ning Empire.
You know it better than anyone.
Shen Zhi Shu, tell me,
do you truly believe
that Meng would betray the Ning Empire
and harm His Majesty?
Under the eyes of everyone,
if you were me, what choice would you make?
Defying His Majesty
and betraying the Ning Empire
like Meng Ting Hui?
Fu Zhi.
Leave me alone.
Fu Zhi, I know
you hate me for this.
If hating me makes you feel better,
you can hate me for as long as you want.
It's not that I'm unwilling to walk with you.
It's just that behind me,
there's the Shen family's
central legacy of honor and loyalty
and the peace that Ning's soldiers
bought with their blood.
I... I do hate you.
I hate that you don't understand
Meng's helplessness.
I hate you
for putting your cold stance
above our feelings.
I hate that you are right.
But I still hate you. I just hate you.
Protecting the Ning Empire is my duty.
And protecting you
is my instinct.
East gate under attack! Quickly reinforce!
- Let's go!
- Quick!
Hurry!
Who set the fire?
Your Highness,
Shadow Guards have raided the grain camp.
It must be the men sent by Ying Gua.
Someone is retreating to the east gate.
After them!
Your Highness.
Your Highness's safety matters most.
Please stay behind to coordinate.
Is it true?
It is true.
Are you really going to marry Shangguan Zhao
and declare yourself empress?
My clansmen were bullied and killed
by Ning soldiers.
Every night when I close my eyes,
a hundred thousand dead souls
are weeping and questioning me in my ears,
"Murong Yao,
why don't you fight?"
If you were me,
how would you choose?
There's never a way to have both.
You love the Ning Empire,
and I love Zhongwan.
On the day of our wedding, you let me go.
So today, I have never seen you either.
From now on,
we are even.
Your Majesty's strategy was brilliant.
First you burned Beijian's grain
and threw them into disarray.
Then you had our army
switch to soft gold-thread armor
and set an ambush at Xigu Pass
to encircle the enemy,
leading to the complete rout
of Beijian's main force.
Beijian lost the first battle badly.
They will counterattack with full force.
We must not let our guard down.
Yes!
Shangguan Zhao,
where is Meng Ting Hui?
She's at the temporary palace,
preparing for the coronation ceremony.
In the battle of Xigu Pass,
you caused Beijian
to lose troops and commanders.
Tell me, has your princess
colluded with the Ning Empire?
Your Highness,
losses are to be expected in battle.
Isn't making rash accusations
before the truth is clear
way too arbitrary?
Shadow Guards of Ning
retreated to the west gate,
and you claimed it was the east gate.
Tell me, are you secretly colluding
with the enemy?
What I saw that night
was indeed the east gate.
Your Highness,
if she truly dares to collude with the enemy,
I will personally finish her off.
I will clean up your house for you!
Mr. Shangguan, your hand!
Shangguan Zhao,
your dog has developed improper thoughts.
Someone, take her away.
Now that Ying Gua's forces
are all concentrated at Xigu Pass,
why not take advantage of his lowered guard
and strike at Jinxia Pass,
the throat of Ning?
[Jinxia Pass]
I want to make Ying Gua watch his realm
turn into a sea of blood.
What have you concealed for Her Highness?
It has nothing to do with her.
The Beijian people are wolves at heart,
never to be trusted.
I don't want you to deal with the devil.
As long as Ning falls,
I don't care what it takes.
It was I who saved you
and taught you swordsmanship.
And now, of all people,
it's you who betrayed me.
I don't want to watch you fall further.
Look at yourself now.
Are you still fighting for Zhongwan's people?
You are filling your own selfish desires
with our people's blood.
If you hate that Her Highness loves Ying Gua,
then go kill Ying Gua.
But don't drag countless people
down with you.
Don't think I won't kill you.
My life was saved because of you.
I'll return it to you.
I'd willingly die
by your hand.
Get lost!
Before I change my mind.
Let's leave together,
far away from these conflicts.
You all say I'm crazy,
but if I weren't,
how could I have endured
the hatred of over ten years?